<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>


<?xml-model href="herschell_09-21_rnc-02.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>

<recipe>
    <title>Country Loaf (Pain de Campagne)</title>
    <author>Deb Lindsey for The Washington Post</author>
    <date>SEP 10, 2014</date>
    <description>Washington author Sam Fromartz has been making sourdough variations of this yeast bread for years. Here, he adds fermented cider for flavor. A mild beer may be substituted; an IPA would be too bitter. The loaf is sized to last a few days.</description>
    <note>The optional tablespoon of water is to compensate for the variable absorption of the rye and whole-wheat flours.</note>
    <utensils>
        <utensil>colander</utensil>
        <utensil>pastry cloth or clean dish towel</utensil>
        <utensil>covered cast-iron or enameled cast-iron pot</utensil>
    </utensils>
    <make-ahead>The dough needs four 20-minute rests, plus an 8-to-24-hour stay in the refrigerator and a final 1 1/2-hour rise.</make-ahead>
    <storage-notes>Store the cooled loaf in a paper bag for a day, and store in a plastic bag for a few days after that. Do not refrigerate.</storage-notes>
    <servings>
        <tested-size>10-12 servings</tested-size>
        <makes>one 11-ounce loaf 10 to 12 slices</makes>
    </servings>
    <ingredients>
        <ingredient amount="1 1/4 cups" weight="160 grams" name="white bread flour" additional="plus more for dusting"/>
        <ingredient amount="1/4 cup" weight="38 grams" name="stone-ground whole-wheat flour"/>
        <ingredient amount="1/4 cup" weight="32 grams" name="stone-ground whole rye flour"/>
        <ingredient amount="1/2 teaspoon" name="instant yeast or bread machine yeast" weight=""/>
        <ingredient amount="1 teaspoon" name="table salt" weight=""/>
        <ingredient amount="1/4 cup" weight="55 grams" name="dry fermented cider" additional="(may substitute Pilsener beer; see headnote)"/>
        <ingredient amount="1/2 cup" weight="120 grams" name="lukewarm water (80 degrees)" additional="plus an optional 1 tablespoon"/>
    </ingredients>
    <directions>
        <step>Whisk together the flours, yeast and salt in a mixing bowl. Combine the cider and water in a liquid measuring cup.</step>
        <step>Add the liquid to the flour mixture; use a spatula or bench scraper or your hand moistened with water to blend them for about a minute. The dough should be shaggy yet cohesive. Cover the bowl with a towel; let the dough rest for 20 minutes.</step>
        <step>Moisten your kneading hand. If the dough seems stiff, add the optional tablespoon of water. Stretch one edge of the dough (still in the bowl), then press it into the center of the bowl. Repeat this about a dozen times, moving clockwise to catch all sides of the dough. (This should take 1 or 2 minutes.)</step>
        <step>Turn the dough over so the seams are on the bottom. Cover and let rest for 20 minutes. Repeat the clockwise stretching and folding two more times, with 20-minute rests after each. Cover and refrigerate at least 8 hours and up to 24 hours. The dough should have doubled</step>
    </directions>
</recipe>